Okay בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is ל"ח *lamed chet*
and we move beyond the אגדתא *Agadata* and continue on with the
משניות *Mishnayot* now
discussing the specific things that are נאמרין בכל לשון be'chol lashon. *ne'emarin
bechol lashon* to be said in any language. And we turn to
ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim, *Birchas Kohanim* and an interesting thing is is
that a lot of the הלכות *halachos* about ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim
*Birchas Kohanim* get discussed here. Like it is interesting, you know, there's
a whole פרק *perek* that's going to be the last פרק *perek*
about עגלה ערופה *Egla Arufa*. Like where in ש"ס *shas* does עגלה
ערופה *Egla Arufa* get discussed? It gets discussed in סוטה *Sota* why?
Because it's mentioned in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* about about in the
discussion about whether you say it in Hebrew or בכל לשון be'chol
lashon *bechol lashon*, so then we devote a פרק *perek* to discussing
the הלכות *halachos* of עגלה ערופה *Egla Arufa* because we're also going
to talk about it. So anyway ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim, *Birchas Kohanim*,
which should have been interesting to have speculated where would be a
good place to put ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim *Birchas Kohanim*, maybe somewhere
in קדשים *Kodshim* or something, or ברכות berachot *Berachos*, I don't know,
anyway so a lot of it is going to be discussed here
in the discussion of this משנה Mishnah, *Mishna*. So let's take a
look or the משנה's Mishnah, *Mishna's* elaboration of the issues about נאמרין
בלשון הקודש bi'lashon ha'kodesh. *ne'emarin be-lashon hakodesh*. So ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim
כיצד *Birchas Kohanim keitzad*? And how is ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim, *Birchas
Kohanim*? ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim? *Birchas Kohanim* is one of the things
that's only בלשון הקודש bi'lashon ha'kodesh, *be-lashon hakodesh*. So the כיצד *keitzad*
though is not saying how do you say it in לשון הקודש
lashon ha'kodesh. *lashon hakodesh*. It's basically using this as an opportunity to
discuss how ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim, *Birchas Kohanim* is how ברכת כהנים
birchas kohanim. *Birchas Kohanim* is done. So במדינה אומר אותה שלש ברכות
berachos *bamedina omer osa shalosh berachos*, you say three ברכות berachos, *berachos*,
ובמקדש ברכה berachah... אחת *ubamikdash bracha achas*, and one ברכה beracha. *bracha*.
Which the now of course the ברכה beracha. *bracha* here does not
mean ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם *Baruch ata Hashem Elokeinu Melech
Ha'olam*, this is the ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim *Birchas Kohanim*, the ברכה
beracha *bracha* is יברכך ה' וישמרך *Yevarechecha Hashem veyishmerecha*, יאר ה' פניו
אליך ויחנך *Ya'er
Hashem panav eilecha viyichuneka*. The question of ברכה beracha אחת *bracha achas*
or שלש ברכות brachos *shalosh berachos* is, do you pause at the
end of each פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to say אמן *Amen* and treat
each thing as a separate ברכה beracha, *bracha* with a separate אמן
*Amen*, or do you say all three פסוקים pesukim *psukim* together? So
in outside of the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*, you do three. In the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* itself, you do not interrupt and
you only say one אמן *Amen* at the end. What's that what's
that about? Or you don't say an אמן *Amen* actually, what's that
about is is that because in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* you don't
respond אמן *Amen*. We'll talk about that in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*.
You say ברוך שם *Baruch Shem*, but that's when you say yeah,
but that's not but that doesn't interrupt sort of the the three
ברכות *berachos*. So so therefore it all constitutes one ברכה beracha *bracha*.
So we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So you
say ברוך שם *Baruch Shem* at the end is what you're saying,
in the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*. Well normally you say ברוך שם *Baruch
Shem* when you say well let yeah let's we'll take a look
in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, okay? But basically you do not interrupt
with an אמן *Amen* in between, so it's all one ברכה beracha
*bracha* in the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash? *Beis HaMikdash*. במקדש אומר את
השם ככתבו *bamikdash omer es Hashem kichsavov*,
in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* you say God's name, the י-ה-ו-ה Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei,
*Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei*, as it is as it is written. So you say the
full the full name of God, you know, the one that's not
pronounced outside of the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. ובמדינה בכינויו
*ubamedina bekinuyov*, and in the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* and outside in the
you know מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*, you say it only in its you
know sort of euphemism or in its its substitute name and if
you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says ככתבו בי"ה,
בכינויו בא"ד *kichsavov be-Yud-Heh, bekinuyov be-Aleph-Dalet*, okay? So you just the way
we we read that word י-ה-ו-ה *Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei* which is, you know, אדון
*Adon* the pronunciation. Okay. במדינה כהנים Kohanim נושאים את ידיהם כנגד כתפיהם
*bamedina kohanim nosim es yedeihen kneged kitfeihen*, outside the בית המקדש Beis
ha-Mikdash? *Beis HaMikdash* the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim* they lift up their
they stretch out their arms opposite their shoulders, you know, sort of
directly shoulder right, no directly sort of parallel, you know, like a
straight line with their shoulders, ובמקדש על גבי ראשיהם *ubamikdash al gabei
rasheihen*, like this, you know, over their heads. So חוץ מכהן גדול
*chutz mikohen gadol*, except for the כהן גדול kohen gadol, *kohen gadol*,
שאינו מגביה ידיו למעלה מן הציץ *she'eino magbiya yadav lema'la min hatzitz*.
It'll be inappropriate for his hands to be above the ציץ *tzitz*.
The reason in general in the in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* their
the hands are above the head is because of the understanding that
the שכינה Shechina *Shechina* rests in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*, the שכינה
*Shechina* rests on the over the you know the hands of the
כהנים kohanim *kohanim*, and therefore the the שכינה *Shechina* should be above
them, you know, so if their hands are here, then the שכינה
*Shechina* somehow parallel to them, you know, in their so their hands
have to be above their heads because but in the what do
you call it, by the כהן גדול kohen gadol, *kohen gadol*, you
don't want their hands to be above the ציץ *tzitz*. Okay. רבי
יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, אף כהן גדול kohen
gadol מגביה ידיו למעלה מן הציץ *af kohen gadol magbiya yadav lema'la
min hatzitz*, no, even the כהן גדול kohen gadol? *kohen gadol* would
do it, שנאמר Shene'emar *shene'emar* as it says וישא אהרן Aharon *vayisa
Aharon* who was a כהן גדול kohen gadol, *kohen gadol* את ידיו
אל העם ויברכם *es yadav el ha'am vayivarchaim*. And how we know
that that was למעלה מן הציץ *lema'la min hatzitz*, I don't know,
but somehow the words וישא *vayisa* presumably means lifted up very high
or something. What? No, I know he was a כהן גדול kohen
gadol *kohen gadol*. How do you know? Because of that word, וישא
*vayisa*. Yeah, וישא *vayisa*, so probably. Okay, so those are three issues
that are addressed, none of them having to do with you know
בלשון הקודש *be-lashon hakodesh*, that's taken for granted, we're using this to
discuss other aspects of it. So whether it's divided into three ברכות
*berachos* or one, whether you say God's name as it's written or
as we tend or as we as we pronounce it, and how
high you lift the hands, shoulder height or above the head. I
do want to point out an interesting organization here in the משנה
*Mishna*, which is it alternates, it says right, exactly, it says במדינה
אומר אותה שלש ובמקדש אחת *bamedina omer osa shalosh ubamikdash achas*, so
it goes מדינה Medinah *medina*, מקדש mikdash. *mikdash*, then it goes מקדש
Mikdash *mikdash*, מדינה *medina*, מקדש Mikdash ככתבו במדינה בכינויו *mikdash kichsavov bamedina
bekinuyov* and then it goes מדינה *medina* and מקדש Mikdash? *mikdash*. So
it could just be that this is, right, it could just be
that this is like a mnemonic, a way that one flows into
the next: מקדש מדינה, Mikdash Medinah, I mean מדינה מקדש, Medinah Mikdash,
מקדש Mikdash. מדינה, מדינה מקדש, Medinah Mikdash, like you know, so it's
just sort of like, you know, it's an ABBA, you know, AB
type of a thing. I also was wondering if also though specifically
when it that it was maybe starting מדינה because that's what's most
relevant, you know, and מקדש Mikdash is historical, but when it got
to the issue of pronouncing God's name, it didn't want to sort
of talk about the pronouncing of God's name the way it was
written, it didn't want to mention that as a- as a secondary
offhand type of a thing, that has to be put front and
center. You know, the other issues are more like historical so they're
mentioned second, but if you're going to talk about pronouncing God's name
fully, you want to pronounce, you know, that to be the first
thing to be said. So maybe they're both true. Anyway, but that's
interesting, the order. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
כה תברכו, Koh tevar'chu, so shall you bless, בלשון הקודש. So first
we start with the issue, not mentioned in this משנה but mentioned
in the opening משנה, that it's in Hebrew. So it has to
be in Hebrew, כה, koh, like this, like the way the words
are written, following, which is in Hebrew. Okay, אתה אומר בלשון הקודש
או אינו אלא בכל לשון? Atah omer bi'lashon ha'kodesh o eino ela
be'chol lashon? Maybe it doesn't mean that, maybe it means any language?
נאמר כאן כה תברכו ונאמר להלן אלה יעמדו לברך את העם Ne'emar
kan koh tevar'chu ve'ne'emar lehalan eileh ya'amdu levarech et ha'am on הר
גריזים. Har Gerizim. מה להלן בלשון הקודש? Mah lehalan bi'lashon ha'kodesh? Because
we learned out there כה, koh, I think the פסוק pasuk there
was what, ככה? kachah? וענו ואמרו, Ve'anu ve'amru, you know, right, so
we need a היקש hekesh between יהודה Yehudah who דרש darshans it
from כה koh
from... right, right. Okay, so there are other דרשות drashot there, but
anyway, but here if כה koh doesn't do it for you, you
have the connection of כה תברכו koh tevar'chu and אלה יעמדו לברך.
eileh ya'amdu levarech. מה להלן בלשון הקודש אף כאן בלשון הקודש. Mah
lehalan bi'lashon ha'kodesh af kan bi'lashon ha'kodesh. Now, before we go further,
just point to an interesting תוספות. Tosafot. ונאמר להלן אלה יעמדו לברך,
Ve'ne'emar lehalan eileh ya'amdu levarech, תימא Teima says תוספות, Tosafot, אדרבה, adarabba,
אימא ונאמר להלן ואכלת ושבעת וברכת. eima ve'ne'emar lehalan ve'achalta ve'savata u'verachta.
מה להלן בכל לשון כדאמרינן? Mah lehalan be'chol lashon ke'damrinan? Why don't
you learn it from ברכת המזון? Birkat Ha'mazon? Also says וברכת, u'verachta,
בכל לשון. be'chol lashon, So ויש לומר דמסתבר ליה טפי למילף ברכת
כהנים מברכת הר גריזים, v'yesh lomar di'mistabra lei t'fei lemilaf birkat kohanim
mi'birkat har gerizim, דשתיהן מפורש בתורה, di'shteihen meforash ba'Torah, there the text
is spelled out in the Torah, what the text is. The ברכות
themselves are also מפורש, meforash, so you have the פסוקים pesukim close
enough, you know, of the ברכה... beracha. I understand, but nevertheless we
do have a whole text in the Torah for that. Okay, so
המפורש ארור האיש הברכה, ha'meforash arur ha'ish ha'berachah, but לשון ברכת המזון
אינו מפורש בתורה, lashon birkat ha'mazon eino meforash ba'Torah, which is
which means that וברכת u'verachta by ברכת המזון, birkat ha'mazon, there's no
text to recite. You would fulfill the דאורייתא De'oraita obligation if you
would say, "Blessed is God for this, you know, for this good
land that God has given us" or something. Meaning there's no text.
So if there's no text, why should I think you have to
say it in Hebrew? The idea of saying it in Hebrew, right,
is an idea of reciting the text as, you know, reciting the
official text in the, you know, in its sort of proper text.
Meaning, I think the question here that תוספות Tosafot is raising is,
right, one way of framing it is, do you have to say
it in the original or can you say it in translation? Right?
So when you have a text, the question of Hebrew or another
language is really, is
really another way of saying that is the question of, do you
have to say the original text or are you allowed to say
it in translation? The original happens to be written in Hebrew. Okay?
Whereas if you were to say something without a text has to
be said in Hebrew, it's a different concept. It's like, it doesn't
matter what words you say, there's an importance of saying those words
in Hebrew. But almost all of the cases we've been dealing with,
well, I don't know, I mean I'd have to check some משנה,
I think almost all of them are ones in which, you know,
maybe that's the difference. Some of those things that are בכל לשון
be'chol lashon are דוקא בכל לשון davka be'chol lashon because there is
no particular text. I mean רש"י Rashi made that point of ואכלת
ושבעת וברכת, ve'achalta ve'savata u'verachta, that since the תורה Torah doesn't give
a text, obviously you could say it בכל לשון, be'chol lashon right?
Now some are בכל לשון be'chol lashon. even though there is a
text, right? פרשת סוטה, Parshat Sotah, וידוי מעשר, Vidui Ma'aser, קריאת שמע,
Kriat Shema, those have a text and בכל לשון means you can
say it in translation. תפילה, Tefillah, ברכת המזון, Birkat Ha'mazon, שבועת העדות
Shevuat Ha'edut and שבועת הפקדון, Shevuat Ha'pikadon, those don't have a formal
text. Okay, so of course they're בכל לשון. But the things that
are only בלשון הקודש, let's talk about what they are. מקרא ביכורים,
Mikra Bikkurim, חליצה, Chalitzah, ברכות קללות, berachot klalot, ברכת כהנים, birchas kohanim
ברכת כהן גדול Birkat Kohen Gadol is interesting, that's one thing that
doesn't have a text. So that's the one exception. פרשת המלך, Parshat
Ha'melech, פרשת עגלה ערופה, Parshat Eglah Arufah, ומשוח מלחמה בשעה שמדבר אל
העם. u'mashuach milchamah be'sha'ah she'medaber el ha'am. All of those have a
text. So part of the point of נאמר בלשון הקודש ne'emar bi'lashon
ha'kodesh is really a way of saying has to be said in
the original, can't be said in translation. So things with a text,
you can discuss original or translation. Things without a text, of course
you can... so an interesting way of rethinking the emphasis of לשון
הקודש. lashon ha'kodesh Is it an emphasis on לשון הקודש or is
it an emphasis on some things you need to do the original
text and you can't do in translation? Which would explain the ones
that are original. The only exception to that, no, meaning there could
be some, what, there are always going to be the differences we
find, fine. But there could be some things you're allowed to say
translation, some things have to be in original. But even, but what
I'm saying is all the things that are in Hebrew,
one way of thinking about it is it's not really about being
in Hebrew, it's really about just saying it in the original. Okay,
the one exception
to
that. You don't have a bigger text than that. Right, that's exactly
it, exactly. So you can have a text and say its translation.
Anyway, that's תוספות's Tosfos point. So here that you're dealing with a
text, we're much more inclined to say that it has to be
in the original and learn it out from something else that has
a text. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: רבי יהודה אומר אינו צריך, eino tzarich, הרי הוא אומר harei
hu omer כה, ko, עד שיאמר בלשון הזה. ad sheyomar balashon hazeh.
I don't need to go to a פסוק pasuk about ברכות וקללות.
berachos ukelalos. כה Ko itself tells me exactly this way. I know.
תניא אידך, Tanya idach, כה תברכו ko sevorechu בעמידה. ba’amida.
So you shall bless, you have to be standing. How do you
know? אתה אומר Ata omer בעמידה ba’amida או אינו אלא o eino
ela אפילו afilu בישיבה? biyoshiva? Maybe you can do it when you're
sitting. נאמר כאן Ne’emar kan כה תברכו ko sevorechu ונאמר להלן vene’emar
lehalan אלה יעמדו לברך. eileh ya’amdu levarech. Again, the link to הר
גריזים והר עיבל. Har Gerizim veHar Eival. מה להלן Ma lehalan בעמידה
ba’amida אף כאן af kan בעמידה. ba’amida. It says יעמדו. ya’amdu. Okay,
so same idea, one's approach is to learn it out from הר
גריזים והר עיבל. Har Gerizim veHar Eival. רבי נתן אומר Rabbi Natan
omer אינו צריך. eino tzarich. הרי הוא אומר Harei hu omer לשרתו
ולברך בשמו. lesharto ulevarech bishmo. That the כהנים kohanim are chosen to
serve God and to bless in God's name. Okay, so מה, ma,
and that is a פסוק pasuk that nicely connects their role as
serving in the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and giving the ברכה. beracha
So that's, I mean that פסוק pasuk is a very like powerful
פסוק pasuk in sort of identifying that as a major role of
the כהנים, kohanim לשרתו ולברך בשמו. lesharto ulevarech bishmo. Right, and so
now we're going to link those two. מה משרת Ma mesharet בעמידה
ba’amida אף מברך af mevarech בעמידה. ba’amida.
So the same way serving God they have to be standing, they
can't be sitting when they're shechting a קרבן, korban, so they have
to when they're blessing they have to be standing. ומשרת גופיה מנלן?
Umesharet gufeih minalan? How do you know that the service in the
מקדש Mikdash, has to be בעמידה? ba’amida? דכתיב Dechtiv לעמוד לשרת, la’amod
lesharet, to stand and to serve. They also serve who only stand
and wait. So okay,
so now this is very conceptually interesting and important because you have
one approach that learns the requirements of ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim either
totally local from ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim כה, ko, ככה, kacha, you
know, כה תברכו, ko sevorechu, or if we're going to have to
draw a comparison, we're going to draw it from something that is
not really specifically to the role of כהנים kohanim per se. It's
about the ברכות וקללות berachos ukelalos and it's also a form of
a ברכה. beracha It's more about a ברכה bracha. than it is
about being a כהן. kohen. Okay, so those will be, that's the
constellation we're going to learn from, as opposed to the second approach,
and this is going to continue in a number of ways in
which no, the constellation of areas we learn it from is their
role in the מקדש. Mikdash. So it could be interesting what differences
could emerge from that, but so far we're all saying the same
thing but learning it from different places. There's also a hermeneutic dispute
going on here as well, right? In other words, it has the
same implications as you're saying, but like do you stick close to
the language and context? If you don't have to, if you can
do it close to the context, it's as if you're saying it's
inappropriate to go out and be more expansive. Yeah, but if you
could do it completely locally maybe everybody would agree, but if you
have to search for something a little external, are you going to
emphasize the ברכה bracha. aspect here or the כהנים kohanim. aspect here?
And that I think is, so that's not a general hermeneutic local
versus looking outside. Either way you have to look outside of the
immediate context or in some of these cases. But I do think
what they're splitting on is do we look at how you do
ברכות or do we look at what כהנים kohanim do? Okay, and
so that's really very interesting. Yeah, one נפקא מינה nafka mina I
can think of from that is if you're looking at ברכות, especially
הר גריזים והר עיבל, Har Gerizim veHar Eival, which wasn't done in
the מקדש, Mikdash. it'd be more likely to have it done outside
of the מקדש. Mikdash Right, so an interesting point to say, alright,
there's less of an impetus to have it done there. Exactly. So
I think an important question is like and on the one hand
the פסוקים pesukim don't say, right? The פסוקים psukim say you know,
don't say the כהנים kohanim only do this in the מקדש. Mikdash,
No, well but it does say, well we'll get to that, right?
But on the other hand if you're learning all of this out
from שירות במקדש, sheirut bamikdash, how do we know there's a
מצוה mitzvah ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim חוץ למקדש? chutz lamikdash? Is what
we do the מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah d'oraisa ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim or
is it some זכר zecher or whatever, right? So the more you
say that this is about שירות sheirut and מקדש, Mikdash, even though
פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk doesn't emphasize that when it speaks
specifically about ברכת כהנים, Birkas Kohanim but it says לשרתו ולברך בשמו,
lesharto ulevarech bishmo, maybe yeah, maybe it is really דאורייתא d'oraisa מקדש
Mikdash limited. So I think it's a very profound debate going on
here. There's actually, well we'll talk about it a little bit more.
Let's get a little further in the
גמרא. Gemara Okay. Okay, תניא אידך, Tanya idach, כה תברכו ko sevorechu
בנשיאת כפיים, binisias kapayim, lifting up the hands. אתה אומר Ata omer
מנשיאת כפיים minisias kapayim או אינו אלא שלא בנשיאת כפיים? o eino
ela shelo binisias kapayim? How do you know it means lifting up
the hands? נאמר כאן Ne’emar kan כה תברכו ko sevorechu ונאמר להלן
vene’emar lehalan וישא אהרן את ידיו אל העם ויברכם. vayisa Aharon et
yadav el ha’am vayevarechem. So there you go, he gave a blessing
to the people, notice also that was
like
בשעת עבודה. bishat avodah.
Okay, so so it is still learning about straight from an an
phenomenon of a ברכה, bracha but it happens to be also like
rooted in a in a reality of מקדש. Nevertheless, let's see what
the other approach is. קשיא ליה לרבי יונתן. Kashya lei leRabbi Yonatan.
So Rabbi Yonatan had was bothered with this. אם כמה להלן Im
kema lalan כהן גדול, kohen gadol ראש חודש rosh chodesh ועבודת ציבור,
va'avodat tzibur, אף כאן af kan כהן גדול, kohen gadol ראש חודש
rosh chodesh ועבודת ציבור. va'avodat tzibur.
If you're gonna learn it out from there, maybe you can only
learn it out very narrowly because they are, you know, Aaron was
a כהן גדול kohen gadol,
and the case there was it was at the מילואים, miluim, it
happened to have been ראש חודש rosh chodesh and it was after
bringing all these קרבנות ציבור. korbanos tzibur. So if we're gonna learn
it out from there, let's let's only learn out that you do
נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim under very narrow circumstances. רבי נתן אומר Rabbi
Natan omer אינו צריך. eino tzarich. Fine, you're right. Don't you don't
need that learning out from Aaron, then you get stuck stuck there
anyway. הרי הוא אומר, Harei hu omer, here's what you learn it
from: הוא ובניו כל הימים. hu uvanav kol hayamim. Now that's the
end of the פסוק pasuk כי בו בחר השם ki vo vachar
Hashem אלהיך Elokecha whatever לעמוד לשרת הוא ובניו כל הימים. la'amod lesharet
hu uvanav kol hayamim.
So it's the end of the פסוק pasuk? לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lesharet.
What is it? No, it's not לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lesharet. לשרתו ולברך
בשמו. Lesharto ulevarech bishmo. Sorry, לשרתו ולברך בשמו lesharto ulevarech bishmo הוא
ובניו כל הימים. hu uvanav kol hayamim.
So it is the am I right? Is that the end of
the פסוק? pasuk. No, I'm sorry, I just made up a פסוק.
pasuk כי בו בחר השם מכל שבטיך לעמוד לשרת בשם השם הוא
ובניו כל הימים. Ki vo vachar Hashem mikol shevatecha la'amod lesharet beshem
Hashem hu uvanav kol hayamim. I was right the first I was
first right the first time. לעמוד לשרת בשם השם הוא ובניו כל
הימים. La'amod lesharet beshem Hashem hu uvanav kol hayamim.
So that is again a פסוק pasuk of לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lesharet.
So again notice the same thing: the first approach, it happened to
be the case that Aaron had just brought the עבודה, avoda, had
just brought the קרבנות. korbanos. But nevertheless the לימוד limud was how
did Aaron do ברכת כהנים? Birkat Kohanim. And we're going to learn
from that how you do ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim. right? So it's
still sort of learning from the act of ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim
The second approach is saying no, we're going to learn from עבודה
avoda of כהנים. kohanim So let's take a look. So הוא ובניו
כל הימים, hu uvanav kol hayamim, מקיש בניו לו. makish banav lo.
So his children are similar to him. מה הוא בנשיאת כפיים, Ma
hu binisiat kapayim, the same way Aaron did it when he gave
that ברכה bracha? by lifting up his hands, אף בניו בנשיאת כפיים
af banav binisiat kapayim when his sons give the ברכה bracha. they
do it by lifting up the hands.
וכתיב כל הימים, Uchtiv kol hayamim, and it says all days, which
means that it's not just under special circumstances ראש חודש, rosh chodesh,
עבודת ציבור, va'avodat tzibur, etc. So you had two questions: number one
was maybe we'll limit it to כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol, No, it's
not limited to כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol הוא ובניו. hu uvanav. Right?
So if he did it with נשיאת כפיים, nesiat kapayim, the sons.
Maybe it's only ראש חודש rosh chodesh and קרבנות ציבור? korbanot tzibur?
כל הימים, Kol hayamim, it's not it's no it's not on special
occasions. Okay, so that tells us don't limit it to that type
of a thing. One minute. Now וכתיב כל הימים, uchtiv kol hayamim,
ואקש ברכה לשרות. va'akesh beracha lesherot. You'll say okay, but that's לעמוד
לשרת, la'amod lesharet, that doesn't tell you you're talking about giving a
ברכה. bracha No, because we have the other פסוק pasuk we said.
ואקש ברכה לשרות. Va'akesh beracha lesherot. We have the other ברכה bracha,
that says לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lesharet. Okay, so what this is saying
is that you have a פסוק pasuk הוא ובניו כל הימים hu
uvanav kol hayamim that says the עבודה avoda is done by Aaron's
children the same way Aaron did the עבודה, avoda, right? And it's
done that way even under normal circumstances, not only special circumstances. That's
a general statement about the עבודה. avoda. And then he says and
since we know ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim is linked to the עבודה,
avoda, so the same way the עבודה avoda is done by the
children like by the like by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, and
they're done, you know, under all circumstances, then the נשיאת כפיים, nesiat
kapayim, the lifting of the hands that Aaron did when he gave
the ברכה bracha is also done the same way even if you're
not a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and even not under special circumstances.
So again what this approach is doing is it is wrapping up
נשיאת כפיים, nesiat kapayim, ברכת כהנים birchas kohanim? as a no as
a type of an עבודה avoda and therefore we're going to sort
of learn how do you know that you do the נשיאת כפיים
nesiat kapayim normal כהנים kohanim not special circumstances? Because that's true about
all the עבודות, avodot, is it's done the same way if you're
כהן kohen or כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, and it's, you know, under
special circumstances or
not
special
circumstances.
So again these two different approaches of whether it's about how ברכת
כהנים birchas kohanim? specifically is done or about something about it's being
part of the עבודה. avoda. Yeah Mike? So what I'm trying to
understand then is it's very interesting because I was always under the
impression that השם המפורש Hashem Hamiforash was so powerful that like, you
know, we really wanted to limit it to only like, you know,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur or whatever it is, only like כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, you know, but now here from מקיש אותו לבניו makish
oto levanav it means all of the כהנים kohanim are using
שם המפורש. Shem Hamiforash. Yeah.
So we'll see, we haven't gotten yet to the outside of the
temple,
but I mean we'll see. It could be that they did it
outside even when there was a temple, they did it outside. Well,
we have to figure out, so let me use this now, now
that I've been framing this as these two approaches, I want us
to turn our attention to this תוספות Tosefos which says:
והיה אומר בכל מקום אשר... ve-hayah omer be-chol makom asher... I'm sorry,
is that תוספות? Tosefos?
No. תוספות
וכתיב כל הימים. Tosefos ve-chtiv kol hayamim. So it says: תימא אכתי
עבודת יחיד מהיכא לן Teima, akati avodas yachid mei-heichalan? תוספות Tosefos says,
these תוספות Tosefos says: I don't get it, even with this דרשה
drasha of כל הימים, kol hayamim, so you don't need special circumstances
like ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but still, you know, how do you
know that you would do it by a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid,
by עבודת יחיד, avodat yachid, meaning the קרבן יחיד? korban yachid? Maybe
you only do it in the context of a קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibbur, because you have קרבן ציבור כל הימים, korban tzibbur kol hayamim,
every day you're bringing a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, the תמיד. tamid.
So how do you know from כל הימים kol hayamim that you
do the, that you do the נשיאת כפיים, nesi'as kapayim, the lifting
of the hands part of it, how do you know you do
it when you're without a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, in the case
by אהרן Aharon, was a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, and כל הימים
kol hayamim occurs also by קרבנות ציבור, korbanos tzibbur, every day you
have a קרבן תמיד. korban tamid. Did they do it outside of
the בית המקדש? Beis ha-Mikdash? Well, he hasn't said that, but he
says: how do you know you do it without? That's almost implicit.
Let's keep on reading. Okay, but that was the challenge. Remember the
challenge was maybe you need it to be כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol.
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So we got rid
of כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, by בניו. banav. We got rid of
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh by כל הימים. kol hayamim. תוספות Tosefos says
how do we get rid of קרבן ציבור? korban tzibbur? Okay. But
I'm just wondering, was it said in the בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash
when was it said, the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim, in the בית
המקדש? Beis ha-Mikdash. Michael, the question is how do we know that
that's the הלכה? halacha? How do we know you do נשיאת כפיים
nesi'as kapayim without all the things that was in the case by
אהרן, Aharon, right? That's the question. We know the lifting of the
hands from אהרן, Aharon וישא אהרן את ידיו אל העם ויברכם. Vayisa
Aharon es yadav el ha-am vayivarkhem. But the question was maybe that's
limited to כהן kohen, גדול, ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, and קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibbur. So we eliminated כהן kohen, גדול by בניו. banav. We
eliminated ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh by כל הימים. kol hayamim. How did
we eliminate קרבן ציבור? korban tzibbur? Well, we didn't. We need, like,
I thought in the actual בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash. it was done
by the תמיד. tamid. So that's the, okay, so that's the question.
But is that, let's read. So then the question is, but how
do you, so are you, okay, so let's read. So the גמרא
Gemara says: מהיכא לן דאצטריכא דאיכא נשיאת כפיים ואף בכל הימים איכא
נמי עבודת ציבור כגון תמיד. Mei-heichalan di-istricha d'ika nesi'as kapayim v'af be-chol
hayamim ika nami avodas tzibbur k'gon tamid. So Michael's already once again
anticipating תוספות's Tosefos answer. So תוספות Tosefos says: ונראה דודאי לדברי הכל
אימר עבודת יחיד נשיאת כפיים. Ve-nireh d'vadai le-divrei ha-kol imer avodas yachid
nesi'as kapayim. You know what? You're right. You don't do ברכת כהנים
Birchas Kohanim by a קרבן יחיד. korban yachid. רב יהונתן נמי רב
שפי נקטיה, Rav Yonasan nami Rav Shipi naktih, when he's thrown in,
he did, it was really just thrown in, but it really isn't,
but it really isn't their challenge, because it's really right that you
don't do, you don't do ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim. by
a קרבן יחיד. korban yachid. דהוה נשיאת כפיים בכל יומא בבית המקדש
עבודת תמיד, De-havah nesi'as kapayim be-chol yoma be-Veis ha-Mikdash avodas tamid, כדתנן
בפרק ה' דסדר תמיד, k'disnan be-perek hei de-seder tamid, ואחר שנתערבו שנתנו
איברים על גב כבש ומחום ירדו להם ללשכת הגזית ומנו בירכו ברכה
אחת והן בירכו, ve-achar she-nisravu she-nitanu eivarim agav kevesh u-machum yardu ba-lan
lishkas gazis u-manuh birchu bracha achas ve-hein barchu, קראת עשרת הדברות שמע
ויאמר שמו, karas aseres ha-dibros shema vayomer sh'mo, etc. etc. והוא הדין
במוספים ובתמיד של בין הערבים. ve-hu ha-din be-musafim u-vatamid shel bein ha-arbaim.
So they only did it with a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. So
תוספות Tosefos says like Michael, you're right, you know what? It only
exists by a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, it doesn't exist by a
קרבן יחיד. korban yachid. But of course then the obvious question is,
but then how do we do it outside the בית המקדש? Beis
ha-Mikdash Right? So maybe outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. is all
just זכר. zecher. How do you know that that's the מצוה? mitzvah?
So you again have it is that if there's one approach is
saying: I completely ignore the issues of עבודה. avodah. I just see
this as a ברכה. bracha So how do I know it's בעמידה?
be-amidah? I learn it from הר גריזים והר עיבל. Har Gerizim ve-Har
Eival. How do I know that it's with נשיאת כפיים? nesi'as kapayim?
When אהרן Aharon did it, he did it with נשיאת כפיים. nesi'as
kapayim. You're going to tell me: oh wait, he was a כהן
kohen גדול, קרבנות... korbanos... what do I care כהן kohen גדול, קרבנות?
korbanos? It's just a question of how do you do the ברכה.
bracha The relevance of the קרבן korban or whatever is completely irrelevant
to this approach. He doesn't see it at all in the context
of עבודה. avodah. So the fact that it had to, all this
עבודה avodah was around it is not a challenge. So according to
that, there'd be no question presumably that it would be done outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash? But this other approach sees it very
much as an עבודה. avodah. How do you know that you do
it בעמידה? be-amidah? You do the עבודה בעמידה. avodah be-amidah. How do
you know that you do נשיאת כפיים? nesi'as kapayim? אהרן Aharon did...
wait wait, if אהרן did it and it's an עבודה, avodah, maybe
it has to be only with קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, only in
this case, only with כהן kohen גדול. And the answer says: okay,
so it doesn't mean כהן kohen, גדול, it doesn't mean ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, but maybe it still does need קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur.
Okay, but that's a very much of an עבודה avodah type of
an approach. That approach you would logically conclude that it would not
be דאורייתא D'Oraisa outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, So let's take
a look as we now continue. Okay. So it says like this.
Okay. תני אידך, Tani Idakh, כה תברכו את בני ישראל, ko sevarachu
es benei yisrael,
בשם
המפורש. beshem ha-mephorash. כה, ko,
because if it's spelled י-ה-ו-ה, so you read it the way it's
spelled. Okay. אתה אומר בשם המפורש או אינו אלא בכינויו? Atah omer
beshem ha-mephorash o eino ela be-kinuyav? Maybe in the way it's, you
know, pronounced with this, normally, א-ד... Aleph-Dalet... תלמוד לומר ושמו את שמי.
Talmud lomar, ve-samu es shemi. You should put
my name. שמי המיוחד לי, Shemi ha-meyuchad li, my unique, my distinctive
name. יכול אף בגבולין כן? Yachol af bi-gvulin ken?
Maybe even outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. you use or you
say it with the שם המפורש? shem ha-mephorash? נאמר כאן ושמו את
שמי. Ne'emar kan ve-samu es shemi.
Many times,
yeah, right, לשום
את שמו שם. Lasum et shemo sham. The place that God has
chosen to place his name there. מה להלן בית הבחירה אף כאן
בית הבחירה. Ma lehallan Beis Habechira af kan Beis Habechira. The place
where God is placed, right? ושמו את שמי, Vesamu et shemi, clearly
it's echoing ושמו את שמי Vesamu et shemi and לשום את שמו.
Lasum et shemo. So if God's place is where God's name is
placed, that's the שם המפורש. Shem HaMeforash. Everywhere else, you do not
use the שם המפורש. Shem HaMeforash. מה להלן בית הבחירה אף כאן
בית הבחירה. Ma lehallan Beis Habechira af kan Beis Habechira. רבי יאשיה
אומר, Rabbi Yoshiya omer, אינו צריך. eino tzarich. הרי הוא אומר, Harei
hu omer, בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי אבוא אליך
וברכתיך. Bechol hamakom asher azkir et shemi avo eilecha uverachticha. So every
place where I mention my name, I will come and bless you.
The Gemara says בכל מקום סלקא דעתך? Bechol makom salka deitach? Really?
Does this make sense?
Wherever I will come and I bless you everywhere? No, because אזכיר
את שמי Azkir et shemi doesn't say it's everywhere, it's just wherever
I'm going to do. If you look at Rashi, בכל מקום סלקא
דעתך? bechol makom salka deitach? Rashi says וכי בכל מקום שם המיוחד
נזכר? Vechi bechol makom shem hamiyuchad nizkar? הכתיב, Haksiv, זה שמי לעולם
וזה זכרי, ze shemi leolam veze zichri, לא כשאני נכתב אני נקרא.
lo keshe'ani nichtav ani nikra. So according to Rashi, the first challenge
is that if we're going to learn from this that's where the
שם המפורש Shem HaMeforash said, we're already starting with an assumption that
you don't say the שם המפורש Shem HaMeforash everywhere. Of course that's
a little circular because we're going to learn out that the שם
המפורש, Shem HaMeforash, its use is limited to the Mikdash by reading
a Pasuk and saying the Pasuk obviously can't mean everywhere because we
know that you don't say the שם המפורש Shem HaMeforash everywhere. So
that's a little circular. Then the next thing Rashi says is ועוד
Ve'od and here's probably the better approach. וכי בכל מקום שכינה באה
ושרה, Vechi bechol makom shechina ba'ah vesharah, דכתיב dechassiv אבוא אליך, avo
eilecha, והוא לא ייחד מקום להזכרת השם. vehu lo yicheid makom lehazkaras
hashem. So what does it mean בכל המקום אבוא אליך וברכתיך? Bechol
hamakom avo eilecha uverachticha? God's presence, now of course you could say
where God's presence is called upon is where God comes, but somehow
there's a sense that this Pasuk sounds a little bit too universal,
a little bit too much like God makes his presence dwell everywhere.
And that can't be. בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי אבוא אליך,
Bechol hamakom asher azkir et shemi avo eilecha, בכל מקום Bechol makom
סלקא דעתך? salka deitach? Really? God's presence and or God's מפורש Meforash
name is everywhere? אלא מקרא זה מסורס הוא. Ella mikra ze mesuras
hu. You have to sort of read it out of order. Here's
how you have to read it. בכל מקום אשר אבוא אליך וברכתיך,
Bechol hamakom asher avo eilecha uverachticha, where I choose to come and
bless you, where I cause my שכינה to dwell, שם אזכיר את
שמי. sham azkir et shemi. There I will cause my name to
be stated. Of course the funny thing is God is not being
מזכיר שמו mazkir shemo but he's having the כהנים kohanim being מזכיר
שמו. mazkir shemo. והיכן אבוא אליך וברכתיך? Veheichan avo eilecha uverachticha? Where
is that place that I will cause my presence to dwell?
בבית הבחירה, Beveis Habechira, שם אזכיר את שמי. sham azkir et shemi.
What
is this בכל המקום bechol hamakom then? Rashi says שילה Shilo and
the places while we were building up to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash? Anyway, שם אזכיר את שמי בבית הבחירה. sham azkir et shemi
beveis habechira. There I will do it. So it's whatever, we can
debate how the Gemara did not have to read the Pasuk that
way, but nevertheless, it's reading the Pasuk that way, where there is
a אבוא אליך וברכתיך, avo eilecha uverachticha, where there's that presence of
God and God is blessing, there's the אזכיר את שמי. azkir et
shemi. Now the
again, the point here though is in terms of our larger
issue that I've been trying to frame,
because I've been leading up to this question about to what degree
is this still right outside of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. So
here we're finally dealing with if the פסוקים psukim are telling us
that you say it in a different way outside of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that seems to be telling us that it's דאורייתא
d'oraysa outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, But let's go back
and look really about what we
said. The first approach said, how do you know it's not שם
המפורש shem hameforash outside the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash. Learn it from
where? ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל, Vesamu et shemi al bnei
Yisrael, שמי המיוחד לי, shemi hamiyuchad li, my distinctiveness, that's
שם המפורש. shem hameforash. יכול אף בגבולין כן? Yachol af bigvulin ken?
נאמר כאן ושמו ונאמר להלן לשום את שמו שם. ne'emar kan vesamu
vene'emar lehallan lasum et shemo sham. מה להלן... Ma lehallan... hold on
a second,
just lost my focus here saying, hold on a second. Yeah,
so I have to tell you that both of these דרשות drashos
do not
raise the question, even the first one, both of them though raise
the question of how obvious it is that ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim
is being understood to apply outside of the בית— I mean it
sounds like
the simple reading of this ברייתא baraita is that according to both
of these approaches, the only difference is whether it's שם המפורש shem
hameforash or not שם המפורש, shem hameforash, but the presumption is is
that it equally applies, the מצווה mitzvah equally applies outside of the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Because although up until now there's been this
emphasis of one approach of עבודה עבודה עבודה, avoda avoda avoda, here
the whole point seems to be just. the question about whether it's
שם המפורש Shem HaMeforash or not, and that it does equally apply
דאורייתא. d'Oraita. But if you but if you actually look at the
דרשות, drashot, interestingly, both דרשות drashot could lead you to think
that even according to both approaches, it's not דאורייתא d'Oraita outside the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. right? The first one in particular and ironically,
the way that I've been trying to frame it, the first one,
you know, says the language of ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל
v'samu et shmi al b'nei Yisrael is the language by ברכת כהנים.
birkas kohanim And that language of ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל
v'samu et shmi al b'nei Yisrael is echoed where it says אשר
בחר ה' אלוהיך לשום את שמו שם. asher bachar Hashem Elokecha lasum
et shmo sham. So, I mean, it's really a direct echo, right?
ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל v'samu et shmi al b'nei Yisrael
and לשום את שמו שם. lasum et shmo sham. So, you know,
you could have said that that is really emphasizing that the place
where שימת שם simat shem occurs is only in the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash. right? So even, I mean that sounds like... Now the
alternative would be to say, and here's a very important way about
thinking about this פסוק pasuk about בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי,
bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi, right? Because the פשט pshat of
that פסוק pasuk which the גמרא Gemara is resisting is exactly that,
that God's God's placing of God's name is not, you know, is
not limited to one place, right? בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי
אבוא אליך וברכתיך. bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi avo elecha uverachticha.
You know, what happens when you put that universal פסוק pasuk up
against המקום אשר בחר ה' אלוהיך לשום את שמו שם? hamakom asher
bachar Hashem Elokecha lasum et shmo sham? One place is chosen לשום
את שמו lasum et shmo and a place בכל המקום אשר אזכיר,
bechol hamakom asher azkir, which sounds like God's place could be anywhere.
What do you do with that? That's a like a very profound
theological question. So what the גמרא Gemara has done is it sort
of rearranged the פסוק pasuk to say no, no, no, this means
in the one place, it doesn't mean every place, right? But on
the face of it, there's a very profound theological difference between the
one place God has chosen and בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי.
bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi.
So one way of thinking about that difference is that that is
exactly the... that that פסוק pasuk בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את שמי,
bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi, it's exactly referencing to the concept
of ברכת כהנים. birkas kohanim. Because ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim is I
choose to put my place my name in one place, המקום אשר
בחר ה' לשום את שמו שם, hamakom asher bachar Hashem lasum et
shmo sham,
but you the כהנים kohanim who live not you don't just live
in, you know, the מקדש or whatever, if you don't think about
a מקדש-centered עבודה, avodah, you live all throughout בני ישראל, b'nei Yisrael,
your role is to כה תברכו את בני ישראל. koh tivarchu et
b'nei Yisrael. And what happens when you're מברך את בני ישראל? mevarech
et b'nei Yisrael? ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל ואני אברכם. v'samu
et shmi al b'nei Yisrael v'ani avarkhem. בכל המקום אשר אזכיר את
שמי. bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi.
How is God אזכיר את שמו? azkir et shmo? He's אזכיר את
שמו azkir et shmo by getting the כהנים kohanim to be ושמו
את שמי, v'samu et shmi, right? So then אבוא אליך וברכתיך ואני
אברכם, avo elecha uverachticha v'ani avarkhem, right? So it's actually quite beautiful.
You understand you understand what I'm saying, right? It's actually, right? There's
the there's the לשום את שמו שם, lasum et shmo sham, לשום
את שמו שם, lasum et shmo sham, that's the בית המקדש. Okay?
So God places His name at the בית המקדש. But the כהנים
kohanim are ושמו את שמי. v'samu et shmi. I am placing I
God am placing my name in the בית המקדש. The כהנים kohanim
are ושמו את שמי, v'samu et shmi, right? And then I will
bless them, ואני אברכם. v'ani avarkhem. I'll bless them wherever there's ושמו
את שמי, v'samu et shmi, which is, that is בכל המקום אשר
אזכיר את שמי. bechol hamakom asher azkir et shmi. So
אזכיר את שמי. azkir et shmi. I'm I'm placing my name only
in one place. But any place where I cause my name to
be mentioned, right, I will come bless you even out there. And
that's what the כהנים kohanim do. They they place my name, I'm
causing my name to be mentioned, and I will come and I
will bless you. So it's actually quite a beautiful way of thinking
about, right, that it's both the universal and the very local. So
I think that that's like a real great פשט pshat in the
פסוקים psukim and sort of understanding what's going on here. Now with
that understood, right, so I think that, you know, the question about
do we then see ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim, as an עבודה avodah
or as not an עבודה, avodah, right? And how much is it
דאורייתא d'Oraita outside of the מקדש? The more it's just about God's
name and a blessing, I think like you can like read the
פסוקים in this way and have that balance. The more it's really
about like a type of an עבודה, avodah, you don't want to
suggest that that sense of God's presence, עבודה, avodah, whatever is outside
of the מקדש. And notice that the second דרשה, drasha, which more
follows the עבודה avodah approach, is the one that actually rearranged this
פסוק pasuk. so that it lost its universal punch. Okay? So I
think that in the end, I mean I think we're a little
bit of maybe I'm I'm going a little bit whatever, anyway, but
I think you get the direction that I'm going in here, which
is that I think that the first approach is not limited to
the עבודה, avodah, it's okay with the idea that there's a שמי,
sh'mi, this is you know, that there's the שם המפורש Shem HaMeforash
when it occurs here, but that doesn't take away from the fact
that it actually, you know, can be in all places as opposed
to the other approach which remains עבודה avodah focused. Yes. True. So...
but we're still saying that even the עבודה avodah focused
approach... I don't know, meaning I'm not saying this I'm not sure
how much that from this ברייתא baraita if you look at the
second approach, so when it says, you know,
it's not clear to me that the second ברייתא is making it
obvious that there's a מצוה mitzvah outside of the בית המקדש. Just
one quick linguistic thing, I know the מקום משורות Mekom Musharot means
you need to rearrange it. Does any word
relate to the word סריס? Saris? I don't know, maybe it just
means like you're chopping things and moving them around. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Although you have some satisfaction that the בכל
מקום אשר אזכיר את שמי bechol makom asher azkir et shemi appears
to be referring
to עבודה Avoda in the
פסוק. pasuk מזבח אדמה תעשה לי. Mizbeach adamah ta'aseh li. Oh well.
Okay. Alright, so, okay. Now, moving on. תני אידך: Tanni Idach: כה
תברכו את בני ישראל. Ko tivarchu et benei Yisrael. אין לי אלא
בני ישראל. Ein li ella benei Yisrael. גרים, Geirim, נשים, Nashim, ועבדים
משוחררים מנין? ve'avadim meshuchrarim minayin? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אמור להם Emor
lahem all of them, לכולהו. lekulahu. תני אידך: Tanni Idach: כה תברכו
Ko tivarchu פנים כנגד פנים, panim keneged panim, face to face, not
that you know, that the כהנים kohanim are facing the back of
the head. Which was the turn around, there was some problem, right?
פנים כנגד פנים. Panim keneged panim. Yeah. So אתה אומר פנים כנגד
פנים או אין לו פנים כנגד עורף? Ata omer panim keneged panim
o ein lo panim keneged oref? Maybe they're facing the back of
the heads. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אמור להם, Emor lahem, כאדם שאומר
לחבירו, ke'adam she'omer lachaveiro, like you're speaking to your friend face to
face. תני אידך: Tanni Idach: כה תברכו Ko tivarchu בקול רם, bekol
ram, loud. או אין לו בלחש? O ein lo belachash? Maybe it
means in a low voice. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אמור להם, Emor
lahem, כאדם שאומר לחבירו. ke'adam she'omer lachaveiro. No, like you would speak,
which means doesn't I guess you don't have to yell it, but
it has to be like audible, fully audible. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
נקטינן, Naktinan, we take the position, בשנים קורא כהנים ולאחד אין קורא
כהן. bishnayim korei kohanim ule'echad ein korei kohen. If there are two
people, then the חזן chazzan you know, then the חזן chazzan says
כהנים kohanim and then they you know, and then but if there's
only one כהן, he doesn't say כהן, the person just starts. שנאמר
Shene'emar, אמור להם. Emor lahem. So it's reading the להם lahem now
meaning not בני ישראל, benei Yisrael, but now it's reading it very
much in a contemporary liturgical context that the caller calls out to
them that they should start. So there needs to be two of
them to call out כהנים kohanim
לשנים. lishnayim. ואמר רב חסדא Ve'amar Rav Chisda נקטינן, naktinan, we also
take
the position, כהן קורא כהנים, kohen korei kohanim, בני ישראל קורא כהנים.
benei Yisrael korei kohanim. But if ישראל Yisrael is leading he doesn't,
which I think we would have thought the
opposite. We don't hold that, right? שנאמר, shene'emar, we will see, אמור
להם, Emor lahem, אמירה משלכם, amira mishelachem, only if you're talking amongst
your own group do you call out to them, not if you're
an outsider. Okay, maybe you don't want the ישראל Yisrael to be
the one telling כהנים kohanim what to do. משלכם תהא. Mishelachem tehei.
והלכתא Vehilcheta is כוותי דאביי ולאו הלכתא כוותי דרב חסדא. kevati de'Abaye
velav hilcheta kevati deRav Chisda. We rule like אביי Abaye that you
say כהנים kohanim when there are two, not when there's one, but
not like רב חסדא Rav Chisda you say כהנים kohanim even when
there's only one. Now of course here we're dealing with something that
seems clearly an אסמכתא, asmachta, right? Whether you call out כהנים kohanim,
or not, you know, is somebody really saying that that's a דאורייתא
de'oraita part of ברכת כהנים? birkas kohanim It seems very much we're
talking about the ישראל Yisrael doing it, right? We're talking about a
contemporary תפילה tefilla liturgical type of a context, which then raises interesting
questions about how much all the previous דרשות drashos were דאורייתא de'oraita
as well, although they seem to be. But again, the key question
that I want to raise is how much is a presumption that
outside of the מקדש it's דאורייתא, de'oraita, how clear is that? To
me, I think that particularly the approach that emphasized the עבודה, Avoda,
sort of you know, that remains very much a question. Okay, so
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara oh, by the way, let
me just show you one important תוספות Tosafot on ל"ח עמוד א'
lamed chet amud aleph before we turn the page, right at the
bottom of הרי הוא אומר. harei hu omer. It says like
this: ונראה לרי Venireh leRi two lines before the lines get wide
in the תוספות Tosafot כהן שבירך ברכת כהנים בישיבה לא עשה ולא
כלום הך איתקש ברכה לשירות וגבי שירות אמור פרק ב' דזבחים דיושב
מחלל עבודה הלכך אף כאן צריך לחזור ולברך מעומד. Kohen shebeirach birchas
kohanim biyishiva lo asa velo klum hoch ishkash bracha lesherus vegabei sherus
amur perek beit deZevachim deyoshev mechallel avoda hilkach af kan tzarich lachzor
ulvarech me'umad. If he gave the ברכה bracha sitting בדיעבד bediavad it
doesn't work, the same way the עבודה Avoda בדיעבד bediavad is no
good and you would have to go ahead and do it again.
So what's interesting is he's learning out something from the עבודה, Avoda,
treating that עבודה Avoda very seriously, right? And מחלל העבודה, mechallel ha'avoda,
so again really emphasizing the עבודה Avoda approach and learning out that
בדיעבד bediavad it doesn't work. This is actually very relevant because it's
an important question about כהנים who is elderly and can't stand, needs
a wheelchair, needs to you know support his weight and so on.
Is it really true that he cannot you know do the ברכת
כהנים? birkas kohanim So partly it's a question about on the one
hand you could say that if you learn it out from the
עבודה, Avoda, you reach the conclusion that the רי Ri reaches, which
is that it's בדיעבד bediavad פסול, pasul, whereas if you learn it
out from the other approach maybe that's not the same conclusion you
would reach, maybe you could. Maybe you could argue it's לכתחילה, lechatchila,
it's not מעכב. me'akev. But the other interesting thing to raise is
that if you learn it out from the עבודה, Avoda, maybe you
could say that that's only when it's in the מקדש, that's only
when it's connected to the עבודה. Avoda. Maybe you don't have the
same requirements when it's not connected to the עבודה. Avoda. The general
הלכה halacha is that you don't do it, but you don't do
it if you can't stand. Even if you can't stand, even if
he can't stand or whatever it is... no, I mean with assisted
whatever, it's a different question, but if he really can't stand, then
if he's like a wheelchair bound, you know, but I think there's
a there's room to argue that you could do it. Well, I've
had that experience. I've been to a דאבנינג davening with a כהן
in a wheelchair. Yeah, and he went up to ברכת כהנים, birkas
kohanim, right? Yeah. And what about the now that we mentioned it,
you know, that we're doing it outside, I don't understand that dichotomy
why in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, all ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they
do ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim, and בחוץ לארץ bechutz la'aretz or not.
Okay, well we haven't got to that yet. That's anyway, that's a
more of a contemporary practice. No, it comes out to what whatever
we'll discuss it. It's אשכנזי Ashkenazi versus ספרדי Sefardi approach. ספרדים Sefardim
do it outside the מקדש. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, believe me, if it's an אשכנזי Ashkenazi ספרדי, Sefardi,
it's not in the גמרא Gemara. already this distinction. Okay, according to
the גמרא Gemara you would do it every day in חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. Right, exactly. The גמרא Gemara assumes you're doing it every
day in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz as well. But again, the question
I'm raising is is it has it been clear that that's outside
of the מקדש. I mean, I think anyway, I'm just repeating what
I said before. Yeah, and what about עם משה im Moshe having
to sit on the אבן even and holding his hands up, even
though he's not expressing a blessing, be connected? Oh, I don't know
because his hands were פרושות אל השמים prusos el hashamayim as opposed
to directed towards the people, so I don't think that's the model.
Okay, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מתאוה לברכת
כהנים. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi minayin sheHakadosh Baruch Hu misaveh lebirchas
kohanim. How do you know that God desires for the כהנים to
give the ברכה? bracha... שנאמר ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל ואני
אברכם. Shenemar vesamu es shemi al Bnei Yisrael va'ani avarchem. You place
my name and I will bless them, which makes it sound like
it's not like, oh, if they want my name placed on them,
then give them the ברכה. bracha. It sounds like I need you
to put their to place my name on them so I can
bless them. Like God wants this to be done. ואמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי כל כהן המברך מתברך. Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi kol
kohen hamivarech misbarech. Any כהן that gives a ברכה bracha is himself
blessed. ושאינו מברך אינו מתברך. Veshe'eino mivarech eino misbarech. But if he's
not doesn't give the ברכה, bracha you won't be blessed. שנאמר ואברכה
מברכיך. Shenemar va'avaracha mevarachecha. I will bless those who bless you. So
a כהן just puts himself into that ברכה bracha of אברהם Avraham
that he gets blessed because he blessed the people. ואמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי כל כהן שאינו עולה לדוכן עובר בשלשה עשה. Ve'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi kol kohen she'eino oleh laduchan over beshlosha asei. Transgresses
three positive מצוות. mitzvos. כה תברכו, Koh sevarachu, אמור להם, Amor lahem,
ושמו את שמי. Vesamu es shemi. Okay, so yeah, you have to,
right? So it's interesting, right? Why first of all, are we giving
encouragement, oh if you don't do it, you're not going to be
blessed, and now we're saying you're actually obligated. You know? So, but
maybe that's the debate, well no, it's not a debate, רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said both of them. Okay, so
anyway, okay, so we'll take a look, but I want also to
say, is it clear that he's talking about in our contemporary context?
He says אינו עולה לדוכן. eino oleh laduchan. So עולה לדוכן, oleh
laduchan, we don't have a דוכן duchan last I checked, okay, in
our שול. shul. I mean, maybe other שולן shuln do, I don't
know. But if he used... but when we but when we talk
about it, we say, oh when you're עולה לדוכן, oleh laduchan, right,
like we call it דוכנינג, duchaning, but that's not a verb. דוכן
duchan is the platform. Okay? So the so the simple פשט pshat
is in the מקדש if you're not עולה לדוכן. oleh laduchan. But
does he mean no, no, no, it means anyone who doesn't go
up when it's time to go up. Okay, so let's keep on
reading. ושמו את שמי. Vesamu es shemi.
מהו דתימא חוששין שמא בן גרושה או בן חלוצה הוא. Mah d'teima
chosheshin shema ben gerusha o ben chalutza hu. We're afraid he might
be a בן גרושה ben gerusha or בן חלוצה ben chalutza and
that's why he's not doing the ברכת כהנים. So he just brings
ill repute on
himself. ולא פליגי, Velo peligi, they don't really debate. הא דסליק לפרקים
הא דלא סליק לפרקים. Ha desalik leprakim ha delo salik leprakim. One
is if he goes up occasionally, then you know he's not a
בן גרושה ben gerusha or בן חלוצה. ben chalutza. The other is
if he never if he never goes up at all, then people
will suspect that he's a בן גרושה ben gerusha or בן חלוצה.
ben chalutza. But every time he doesn't go up, he's עובר over
on these עשה'ס. aseis. Now interestingly, רש"י Rashi says לפרקים, leprakim, רש"י
Rashi says בחגים ובמועדים. bechagim uvmoadim. Which says oh, that sounds familiar.
So
I wonder what the difference of חג chag and מועד moed is.
Does he mean חול המועד? Chol Hamoed? So that might be. So
we don't do it on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. But anyway, רש"י
Rashi already acknowledging that maybe there's a, why doesn't he say בשבתות
ובחגים? beshabbasos uvchagim? Is he might reflect like אשכנזי Ashkenazi practice, you
know, about that it's only during during יום טוב? Yom Tov? So
what? That's not what he means, you think? I do think he
means that, but I don't think that's necessarily פשט pshat in the
גמרא. Gemara, All the גמרא Gemara means is if every now and
then he goes up, nobody thinks he's a בן גרושה. ben gerusha.
Right? Why does רש"י say oh, if he goes up just on
יום טוב? Yom Tov? Because then people will know, they'll be able
to see that פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara is that nobody's
going to think he's a בן גרושה ben gerusha if sometimes he
goes up and sometimes he doesn't go up. They'll think he's lazy,
they won't think he's a בן גרושה. ben gerusha. רש"י all of
a sudden decides to say that it means he goes up דוקא
davka on יום טוב. Yom Tov. I think he's right. I think
he's reflecting אשכנזי Ashkenazi contemporary אשכנזי Ashkenazi practice. Okay. ואמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי כל כהן שאינו עולה בעבודה שוב אינו עולה. Ve'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi kol kohen she'eino oleh ba'avoda shuv eino oleh.
If you don't go up, and now the same רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi who quoted these עשה'ס aseis and I
was I was raising questions of do we mean again in the
מקדש, outside of the מקדש, whatever. Here he's clearly talking about in
the שול shul context, which also makes the עולה דוכן ole dukhan
in those other statements seem to be very clearly in the שול
shul context. If you don't go up while they're in the middle
of רצה, Retzei, then don't go up, right? Because the ברכת כהנים
comes after the ברכה bracha of רצה. Retzei. But if you didn't
go up while the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur was doing רצה, Retzei,
you can't go up after the ברכה bracha is over. שוב אינו
עולה, shuv eino oleh, שנאמר, Shene'emar, וישא אהרן את ידיו אל העם
ויברכם, vayisa Aharon es yadav el ha'am vayivarkhem, וירד מעשות החטאת והעלה
והשלמים. vayered me'asos hachatass vehaholah vehashlamim.
He blessed them and then came down after bringing the קרבנות, korbanot,
so the blessing was still in the context of the קרבנות. korbanot.
He hadn't even descended from the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So you have to
be... the ברכה bracha has to be taking place in the context
of the קרבנות, korbanot, so even if it's made after the end
of רצה, Retzei, you have to be... it has to be in
that context. You have to be going up to the דוכן duchan
while we're talking about the עבודה. avodah. So here you have the
idea very much that even when it's in the שול shul and
it's not in a מקדש at all, we have to situate it
in the context of the עבודה. avodah. Yes? I'm having with the
choreography. Weren't the לויים Levi'im on the
דוכן? duchan? That's where they sang from, no? Yeah, you're right. I
have to check. There's a different דוכן duchan I think we're talking
about. I'll have to get back to you on that. It gets
crowded. No, no, no. I think we're talking about a different... We
say ותחזינה v'techezeina also, right? I mean, we say ותחזינה, v'techezeina, and
there's that רצה... Retzei... Yeah, but till you get to the end
of the
ברכה... bracha Till you get to המחזיר שכינתו לציון, hamachazir shechinaso l'Tziyon,
the whole ברכה. bracha. Okay. איני, aini, says the גמרא, והאמר רב
אמי ורב אסי סלקי. veha'amar Rav Ami v'Rav Assi salki. רב אמי
ורב אסי Rav Ami and Rav Assi apparently were כהנים, went up
to do ברכת כהנים after the ברכה bracha, of המחזיר שכינתו hamachazir
shechinaso or שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד. she'oscha levadcha b'yira na'avod. That's also,
by the way, interesting. The שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד she'oscha levadcha b'yira
na'avod is actually a different נוסח nusach of the ברכת רצה birchas
Retzei that exists in manuscripts and whatever, and it seems that at
a certain stage there was a convention to... I mean, some of
this is true about like, for example, the ברכה bracha about that
some people say the ברכה bracha, of עושה השלום oseh hashalom on
עשרת ימי תשובה, Aseres Yemei Teshuvah, המברך את עמו ישראל בשלום, ha-m'varech
et amo Yisrael bashalom, and really it was never like, say, oh,
let's do something different for עשרת ימי תשובה, Aseres Yemei Teshuvah, like,
you know, let's construct a new נוסח הברכה. nusach habracha. Really it
was that there were always these two חתימות chatimos in competing liturgies,
and in the end it was sort of, you know, one became
the standard and one became used only during עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseres
Yemei Teshuvah. I mean, some people don't use it during... I don't
use it during עשרת ימי תשובה Aseres Yemei Teshuvah either, but for
those who do. But the point is that they were existing competing
ברכות and it got resolved that way. So the same is true
about המחזיר שכינתו לציון hamachazir shechinaso l'Tziyon and שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד.
she'oscha levadcha b'yira na'avod. Although I do personally think that... so it
wasn't like it was specifically constructed for ברכת כהנים. If you think
about it, you know, ספרדים Sfaradim where they do ברכת כהנים every
day, ספרדים Sfaradim מנהגים, minhagim, did they say שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד
she'oscha levadcha b'yira na'avod on יום טוב? Yom Tov? They don't. Okay,
but I think again, for אשכנזים Ashkenazim at least, I think you
understand it. שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד, she'oscha levadcha b'yira na'avod, המחזיר שכינתו
hamachazir shechinaso is like future-oriented. When you end the ברכה bracha, ביראה
נעבוד, b'yira na'avod, it's עבודה, avodah, and then you go into ברכת
כהנים, right? It much more sort of situates it, you know, as
an עבודה. avodah. So what? I have a question on the נוסח.
nusach.
I'm pretty sure earlier... I'm pretty sure... No, not in the תלמוד,
Talmud, no, no, no. It's like in מודים... Modim... like מודים דרבנן.
Modim d'Rabbanan. Yeah, anyway, in the
גמרא already... it's מודים. Modim. But this, I'm pretty positive it's before
the...
Anyway, so they went up presumably only after the חתימת הברכה. chasimas
habracha. So didn't they go up only after the חתימת הברכה? chasimas
habracha? So the גמרא says: רב אמי ורב אסי מעיקרא הוו עקרי
כרעייהו, Rav Ami v'Rav Assi meikara havu akiri kora'aihu, מטו לא הוו
מטו. matu lo havu matu. No, no, no, they started lifting up
their legs. You know, they started moving a little bit. They just
didn't get all the way up until after, but the process began.
מטו התם. matu hasam. וכדתני רבי
אושעיא, Ukid'tani Rabi Oshaya, like רבי אושעיא Rabi Oshaya teaches, לא
שנו אלא שלא עקר, lo shanu ela shelo akar, oh my god,
what time it is, לא שנו אלא שלא עקר רגליו. lo shanu
ela shelo akar raglav. This idea that you have to... you know,
that you have to... what do you call it? You know, start
going up and you can't go up after the end of the
ברכה bracha is only if you didn't lift up your leg. אבל
עקר רגליו, aval akar raglav, once you lift up your leg, עולה,
oleh, then you can go up even after the ברכה bracha. was
over. ותנן נמי, ut'nan nami, and we taught similarly: אם הבטחתו שנושא
כפיו וחוזר לתפלתו, im havtachto she-nosei kapav ve-chozer litfilato, רשאי. rasha'i. If
the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur is himself a כהן, is he allowed
to do ברכת כהנים or are we afraid that he'll get confused?
So we say, you know what, if he's certain that he can
do ברכת כהנים and afterwards return to his role as שליח ציבור
shliach tzibur and not get like all פוצמומט futzimumt about where he's
up to, then he's permitted to do that. ובינה בה, vavina bah,
we ask: הלא עקר? halo akar? How could he do that? He
didn't... it's good that he wants to do the ברכת כהנים, but
when he was doing the ברכה of רצה, Retzei, he didn't start
moving up to the בימה. bimah. He's standing in the middle of
שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So you
know... Okay, you know what? You don't even have to literally lift
up your foot. You just have to like, you just have to
move a little bit. I don't know, like, you know, you jump
forward
a half a centimeter, you know, you jumped forward. So הכא נמי
דעקר פורתא, Hacha nami de'akar porta, you began to move even a
slight little movement, even if you didn't even displace your position, the
slight beginning of the movement is enough to situate you in the
עבודה. Avoda. Okay, I don't know why. Okay, anyway, ואמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, and Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
also says, אין נותנים כוס של ברכה לברך אלא לטוב עין. Ein
nosnim kos shel bracha livaresh ela letov ayin.
Now this on the one reason which we're just quoting this because
it's another statement of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, but on the other
statement we're talking about an attitude towards giving a ברכה. Because anybody
giving a ברכה, similarly, you don't give the person to give the
ברכה in ברכת המזון Birchas HaMazon unless he by nature is of
a generous type of a disposition. Because you want the ברכה, it's
not just words, you want them to be an expression, you know,
God should bless you and you should have all good things and
it should come from somebody who is of good heart, of generous
heart. שנאמר טוב עין הוא יבורך, Shene'emar tov ayin hu yevorach,
the good of eye, he will be blessed. כי נתן מלחמו לדל,
Ki nasan milachmo ladal, he gave from his bread to the poor.
אל תקרי יבורך, Al tikrei yevorach, do not read "will be blessed,"
אלא יברך, ela yevarech, so he'll also be the one to give
the blessings. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
מנין שאפילו עופות מכירים בצרי עין? Minayin she'afilu ofos makirim betzarei ayin?
How do you know that those that are stingy, even the birds
know who the stingy people are? שנאמר, like your whole attitude, you
communicate your attitude without words. I think it's very powerful again what
he's saying. Somebody is giving a ברכה, it's not just the words
that you're saying. You want somebody with a generous attitude and the
way it's expressed. So similarly, somebody who's stingy, you know, even birds
who don't understand language, they can sense a stingy person. You communicate
it even to the birds. שנאמר כי חנם מזורה הרשת בעיני כל
בעל כנף. Shene'emar ki chinam mezora hareshes be'einei chol ba'al kanaf.
Because like, you know, for nothing is the one who,
what is it? Rashi says the one who scatters the bread in
the net. What they would do is they scatter seed in the
net to get the birds to come and take it. So this
is a פסוק that's again in the context of a stingy person
and it says a stingy person for naught is he trying to
scatter his seeds in the nest for all the birds because the
birds aren't going to come and take it. Who wants to take
the seeds of a stingy person? So you throw out your seeds,
they know you're stingy, they don't want to have anything to do
with you. Okay? But again I think the power is you're going
to give a ברכת כהנים, you know, there's a way you give
a ברכה and it's much more also the non-verbal part that's communicating
the ברכה. Okay and we'll just read one more line about this.
ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
where were we? ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי כל הנהנה מצרי עין
עובר בלאו. Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi kol haneheneh mitzarei ayin over
belav. Anybody who benefits from a stingy person transgresses a negative commandment.
שנאמר אל תלחם את לחם רע עין, Shene'emar al tilcham es lechem
ra ayin, do not have the bread of the one of bad
eye. כי כמו שער בנפשו הוא, Ki kemo sha'ar benafsho hu, it's
like a
pained soul. אכול ושתה יאמר לך, Echol usheseh yomar lach, eat and
drink he will say to you, but ultimately he doesn't want you
to. He might in his words say, "No, no, no, it's okay,
you can have it," but it's very clear that he doesn't want
you to have it. So you're almost like stealing it from him.
Okay? So even his, you know, so not only is he obviously
doing the wrong thing, but like you've got to stay away from
him because he's really not offering you what he says he's offering
you. ורב נחמן אמר ואיתימא, VeRav Nachman amar ve'isayma, עובר בשני לאוין.
over bishnei lavin. אל תלחם ואל תתאו, Al tilcham ve'al sis'av, do
not eat with his bread and do not desire it. Okay so
we will end with this, I guess we'll end with this right
now and we'll continue tomorrow.